<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4006 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4006.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6733 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7155 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7155.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="info" docName="draft-bertz-dime-predictunits-00" ipr="pre5378Trust200902">
 <front>
   <title>Diameter Predicted Units</title>

   <author fullname="Lyle Bertz" initials="L." surname="Bertz">
     <organization>Sprint</organization>
     <address>
       <postal>
         <street>6220 Sprint Parkway</street>
         <city>Overland Park</city>
         <region>KS</region>
         <code>66251</code>
         <country>United States</country>
       </postal>
       <email>lylebe551144@gmail.com</email>
     </address>
   </author>

   <date year="2016" />

   <area>Operations and Management Area</area>

   <workgroup>Diameter Maintenance and Extensions</workgroup>

   <keyword>diameter</keyword>
   <keyword>charging</keyword>

   <abstract>
<t>
    This document specifies the conveyance of predicted usage
    information for proper dimensioning of network services
    that use Diameter based authorization.
</t>
   </abstract>
 </front>

  <middle>
   <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
<t>
   When a User is authorized to use a service via Diameter
   applications such as <xref target="RFC4006"/> or <xref target="RFC7155"/>, the Client is
   not aware of the average load placed upon it by User.  This can
   lead to overload situations or the Diameter Client redirecting or
   denying services to valid Users even though their presence may
   overload the service.
</t>
<t>
   Given virtualization and the use of many software based services
   the service capacity varies on a service instance, i.e. Diameter
   Client, basis.
</t>
<t>
   This specification introduces the Predicted-Service-Units
   Attribute Value Pair (AVP).  This information conveys the
   predicted usage introduced on the service by the authorized User.
   Such information can be used by the Diameter Client to estimate
   future load and proactively manage its resources.
</t>
<t>
   Although this informaiton is conveyed from the Diameter Server to
   the Client several system aspects are out of the scope of this
   document:
  <list style="symbols">
<t>
   How the Diameter Server acquired the information contained in the
   Predicted-Service-UnitsAVP.
</t>
<t>
   How the values in the Predicted-Service-Units AVP were determined.
</t>
<t>
   The accuracy or validity of the values in the
   Predicted-Service-Units AVP.
</t>
<t>
   Specific actions the Diameter Client should take when its service
   functions are overloaded.
</t>
<t>
   Specific actions the Diameter Client takes to bring itself in/out
   of service for new or existing Users.
</t>
  </list>
</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Terminology" anchor="terms" >
<t>
    In this document, the key words "MAY", "MUST", "MUST NOT", "OPTIONAL",
    "RECOMMENDED", "SHOULD", and "SHOULD NOT", are to be interpreted as
    described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>
   </section>
<section title="Predicted Service AVPs" anchor="avps">
   <section title="Predicted-Service-Units" anchor="predictedunits">
  <t>
   The Predicted-Service-Units AVP (AVP Code TBD1) is of type Grouped and
   contains the amount of units that the Diameter credit-control client
   can expect to provide to the end user until the service must be
   released or the new Credit-Control-Request must be sent, if a
   Granted-Service-Unit AVP <xref target="RFC4006"/> has been applied
   to the user's service.  A client is not required to implement all
   of the unit types, and it must ingore unknown or unsupported unit
   types.
</t>
<t>
   The Predicted-Service-Units AVP is defined as follows (per the grouped-
   avp-def of <xref target="RFC6733"/>):
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
         Predicted-Service-Units ::= < AVP Header: TBD1 >
                                    [ CC-Time ]
                                    [ CC-Money ]
                                    [ CC-Total-Octets ]
                                    [ CC-Input-Octets ]
                                    [ CC-Output-Octets ]
                                    [ CC-Service-Specific-Units ]
                                   *[ Service-Cost-Information ]
                                   *[ AVP ]

]]>
</artwork></figure>
<t>
    With the exception of the Service-Cost-Information AVP, all AVPs
    are defined in <xref target="RFC4006"/>.
</t>
<t>
    The presence of this information is provided as anticipated load
    information to the Diameter Client and is not intended to be
    prescriptive in any manner regarding the user's service.
</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Service-Cost-Information" anchor="servicecost">
<t>
   The Service-Cost-Information AVP (AVP Code TBD2) is of type
   Grouped, and it is used to return the service cost information,
   which the client can use, if it understands it, for various
   purposes inclduing load prediction and sizing.
</t>
<t>
   A client is not required to implement all
   of the unit types, and it must ingore unknown or unsupported unit
   types.
</t>
<t>
   It is defined as follows (per the grouped-avp-def of [RFC6733]):
</t>
<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
          Service-Cost-Information ::= < AVP Header: TBD2 >
                                     { Unit-Value }
                                     { Cost-Unit }
                                     { Service-Dimension }
]]>
</artwork></figure>
<t>
    Unit-Value and Cost-Unit are defined in <xref target="RFC4006"/>.
</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Service-Dimension" anchor="servicedim">
<t>
    The Service-Dimension AVP (AVP Code TBD3) is of type UTF8String.
    It specifies the applicable service type (dimension) to the
    Service-Cost-Information.
</t>
  </section>
</section>
<section title="Usage Examples" anchor="usage">
<t>
    When Predicted-Service-Units are returned as part of an
    authorization per <xref target="RFC7155"/> or <xref target="RFC4006"/>, the client MAY use
    this information as guidance on projected load the new
    user will generate on the service.
</t>
<t>
    If the client supports/understnds the information provided in the
    Predicted-Service-Units AVP, it can update it's projected load.
    Based upon this information it MAY take one or more of the
    following actions (this is not exhaustive):
<list style="symbols">
<t>
    Redirect at the service / protocol level any new service requests.
</t>
<t>
    Begin enforcing mechanisms to reduce the amount of service load
    on a subset of services already established.
</t>
<t>
    Remove itself from any system that directs new service requests
    to it.
</t>
<t>
    Initiate administrative functions to increase its capacity or
    start the process of creating new intances to service requests.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

   <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
   IANA allocated AVP codes in the IANA-controlled namespace registry
   specified in Section 11.1.1 of <xref target="RFC6733"/> for the following AVPs that
   are defined in this document.
</t>
<texttable>
  <ttcol>AVP</ttcol>
  <ttcol>AVP Code</ttcol>
  <ttcol>Section Defined</ttcol>
  <ttcol>Data Type</ttcol>

  <c>Predicted-Service-Units</c>
  <c>TBD1</c>
  <c><xref target="predictedunits"/></c>
  <c>GROUPED</c>

  <c>Service-Cost-Information</c>
  <c>TBD2</c>
  <c><xref target="servicecost"/></c>
  <c>GROUPED</c>

  <c>Service-Dimension</c>
  <c>TBD3</c>
  <c><xref target="servicecost"/></c>
  <c>UTF8String</c>
</texttable>
   </section>

   <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
<t>
   The Diameter base protocol <xref target="RFC6733"/> requires that each Diameter
   implementation use underlying security; i.e., TLS/TCP, DTLS/SCTP or IPsec.  These
   mechanisms are believed to provide sufficient protection under the
   normal Internet threat model; that is, assuming that the authorized
   nodes engaging in the protocol have not been compromised, but that
   the attacker has complete control over the communication channels
   between them.  This includes eavesdropping, message modification,
   insertion, and man-in-the-middle and replay attacks.  Note also that
   this application includes a mechanism for application layer replay
   protection by means of the Session-Id from <xref target="RFC6733"/> and CC-
   Request-Number, which is specified in this document.  The Diameter
   credit-control application is often used within one domain, and there
   may be a single hop between the peers.  In these environments, the
   use of TLS/TCP, DTLS/SCTP or IPsec is sufficient.  The details of TLS/TCP, DTLS/SCTP or IPsec
   related security considerations are discussed in the <xref target="RFC6733"/>.
</t>
<t>
   Because this application conveys past usage information (directly or
   indirectly), it increases the interest for various security attacks.
   Therefore, all parties communicating with each other MUST be
   authenticated, including, for instance, TLS client-side
   authentication.  In addition, authorization of the client SHOULD be
   emphasized; i.e., that the client is allowed to perform credit-
   control for a certain user.  The specific means of authorization are
   outside of the scope of this specification but can be, for instance,
   manual configuration.
</t>
<t>
    The attributes provided by this solution MUST be assumed to be
    privacy sensitive by both the client and server.
</t>
   </section>
 </middle>

 <back>

   <references title="Normative References">
     &RFC2119;

     &RFC4006;

     &RFC6733;
   </references>

   <references title="Informative References">
     &RFC7155;
   </references>
 </back>
</rfc>
